Previously, we've seen how to fix sliding issues of our foot, but we had to know when
the contact were happening.
Now we might want to do this automatically, and this is the purpose of this paper.
Hi, I'm Jérôme, and today we'll be looking at knowing when to put your foot down, a paper
from 2006.
This paper would basically use a model that you train on a few animation examples, and
we try to extrapolate on all the animation data you have. So for this what I would do is that I
will first load my character of course. I have a few constants that I will need later and finally
what I would do is that I will load a bunch of animations and I have different walking style
with coming from different actors. I have running animation, I get the dance animation, I get aiming
animations. So quite a lot of different types of animations. So I have different types of
foot contacts that I will be able to learn in the system. So I get running, I get walking
backwards, I get a bunch of dance animations right in the middle there. A lot of different types of
animations that we will be able to learn from. And if I look at how much data I have loaded this
time, I have 22,600 frames of animations that I would want to use to learn what foot contacts
look like. So how this paper works, basically the idea is to train what they call an oracle
that is able to look at your foot animations and tell you if it's a contact with the toe
heel for the left toe, left heel or right toe, right heel. So what we will build first
is the feature vector that represents the data that we will feed to the system to
to learn from.
And it's not just the entire animations we give him,
we will just give a feature vector
that has the position of the toe, heel,
and knee of both legs,
but not only for the specific frames,
but also for the frames,
for an entire windows of frames before and after.
So you basically look at a big windows of frames
with the trajectories of all those positions for the heel, toe, and knee. And that's how
you predict if at frames, right in the middle, if it's a contact or not. So that's the feature
vectors that we're trying to build. What they had as a window, what they said they were using
a 10 frames windows before and after, but the paper is actually running at 60 frames per second.
Only at 30 frames. So my windows will only be five frames before and five frames after.
And what we will create is this, I will compute it for the entire animation at once,
so I don't have to recompute that every time I need to compute the feature vectors.
So I will compute it once, so I get all my animations, all my frames,
then I get my six bones I want to use, I get the XYZ positions in space of
my six bones. And I do it for the entire windows of frames, so for my frames and for the five
frames before and the five frames after. That gives me my feature vectors here. And I have a
second one, which is a feature vector indices, basically will allow me to find back from my
feature vectors, which frame animations it corresponds to, because I will have all my
animations into one big feature vectors, but it's actually a bunch of different
animations with different timing in it. So I need to be able to trace that back.
And basically what they say is that the positions and orientations is irrelevant,
irrelevant to know if you have a contact or not. So what we want to do is to make sure that
every feature vectors is basically realigned in zero zero.
So it all looks the same. We really look at the trajectory of the foot itself and not
where it was in space. So what I will do for this is that I will project my hips on the ground
to use it as the root motion, let's say, and I will compute the position of the
foot for the entire windows of frame at that specific position in space.
So probably easier to show and to explain what I was doing here.
So I compute all my feature vectors and now basically the feature vector is this.
You get all those little arrows, little dots.
So here we are.
And so if I take this for instance, it's one feature for one specific frame.
So and you get so you could actually see the motions itself.
So it's all stable, but that's the feature vector that the Oracle will see, right?
And so now that we have the feature vectors, we could start to try to do the training.
And to do the training, what would happen is that we will use a k-nearest neighbor classifier to
to classify all those feature vectors and give them a label.
But we'll have to do the training by hand first.
And what they do is that they go for a 200 frames sequence
at once.
So they slice the entire animations a bunch of clips.
And you do the training on one clip.
And we will iterate with that kind of stuff.
what I would do is the same thing here. I will start to train my oracle. So I have my trained
feature vectors and I will have my trained label that tells me if I have contacts or not.
And at this point, they're just empty because I haven't trained anything.
And I will start to manually train one clip. And the thing I would do, I'll execute this,
I would pick basically the first clip inside of animation.
So I take the 200 first frames of animations
in my entire system because I don't
have anything better to start from.
So let's start with the beginning.
And so now that I would have this big code here, which
actually is just there to let me see the data I'm looking at
and the contacts I have.
So this is the piece of animations
that will start to train, sorry.
So that's the piece of animation
that we start to train manually for him to learn from.
And basically, because I have nothing at this point,
you can see I get no contact.
But if I come here and I start to click,
I will actually have the representations
of the contact that's happened here
and I could do it for both heel.
So you could see tons of green
when I say that this is a contact.
I will not do it entirely manually under first step
because I would be really annoying
to go through all of this.
So what I would do is that I would generate using speed
as we were doing in the other papers before,
but I will use bigger range.
And then I can start to tweak my data as well.
as long as I decide that this is still a contact.
So foot contact, that's fairly good.
And I would probably, sorry, here I'm back.
And so I will start to tweak this manually
for each of my animations.
Make sure that it is correct most of the time.
And I will probably speed this up
so you don't see me going in the same doing this by hand.
by hand. So I see you when this is done. And now basically, I have tweaked by hand all my
contacts. So I'm making sure that they look like what I want them to be. And so I have
one piece, I have one clip that I've done manually, and I can start to train my oracle
with what I've done so far. So what I would do is I would take the trained feature vector
and I would concatenate what I already trained with the new clips I've just done. So this is just to
grow slowly what data I've actually trained. So my trained vector is just growing
as with my label which means now that I actually have my trained feature vectors
and I will be able to start to use the KNRs neighbor classifier. What they do
with the KNRs neighbor classifier is basically feed all the features
they've trained and all the label into it and then we will use it to predict in the futures.
But to win some time, we will not only give the trained feature vectors, we will also
give the mirrored version because everything we've done on one side is actually applicable for
mirrored animations. So what I will do is that I will mirror the trained feature vectors just by
multiplying the x values because basically I've made sure that everything is aligned
around the zero zeros and the rotation so I can just mirror the feature vectors and I can
mirror the label which is what I'm doing here. So the classifier itself will have a much bigger
train feature vectors which will have everything that I have done plus everything mirrored and I can
fit this into a nearest neighbor class from scipy because luckily enough it's already
written for us and it is extremely fast as long as you just use the default Euler distance matrix
And so we will use that one because it gives us a really big boost in performance and it's really easy to do
In the paper, they were using also the nearest neighbor, but they were doing it themselves with the brute force manner
And they use the error distance anyway, so we could just use what exists for us and
Use the speed as much as we have so we've
train a classifier with the nearest neighbor with the number of neighbors equal to 10 which is again
the values they were using so whatever we give you is as soon as you're trying to ask for a position
inside of a feature vectors it will return the 10 closest one which is what we're interested in
and then we've trained the the nearest neighbor now the the oracle can start to do predictions
so we do need to be able to predict. And how do you predict if a specific feature is a
food contact or not? Basically what we do is that we take the 10 nearest labels to the one we have
have. And then we sum them and we divide by the total. So it's just a probability that
the classifier give us compared to everything else it has seen. So if you have a probability
over 60%, we will say that it is a contact. If we have a probability that is less than
40%, it is not the contact. And if the probability we find is between 40% and 60%, we basically
switch only depending on the previous frame. So if we say I'm in 0.5 and the previous frame
says I was in contact, I'm still in contact. If I'm 0.5 and the previous frame said I was
not in contact, I'm not in contact either. So it's just to avoid jittering values that
if you're always between 0.5, 0.5 and that kind of stuff,
it's too avoid to have on, off, on, off, on, off.
It's just we smooth the signal by saying only when we were sure it was on,
if you're unsure we're still on and then as soon as we're sure it's not, we're not.
So this is what the predict function will do.
We give him a feature, well it's multi-dimensional inside of sci-pi.
So the features itself could be only one specific frame, but it's more interestingly,
it could be an entire animation, so they will tell you the label for the entire animations
this way. So this is what I do, compute the probabilities. So I'm asking the classifier
for the 10 nearest indices, then find the values inside of those labels,
divide it by 10 and then check if it's less or more and if it's in between I
make sure that it follows the rules. So that returns a label. Now I have the
neighbors. The oracle is able to predict but how well we did predict it would
probably be really bad because we really train it on really small data. So the
The idea now is to iterate through the training process as long as you need.
And the idea to do this is basically what they've done, I guess they talk it about
the important sampling.
So that's that here.
So what do we do now that we have a training system?
What I could do is I could ask the classifier to actually look into all my animations and
tell me which frame has the worst possible distance between all my features.
So basically, the clean nearest neighbor will have a bunch of features that will be in space
around here, and all my animations will be around there also.
But I might have animations that will be really far for which I haven't trained anything.
And they're asking to find me the frame of animations that is the furthest away from
anything he has seen already.
And when I have that frame, I find the clip around that one that I have to train.
And I will start to do the training on that one.
So I make sure that I basically, I will start to train the system to see the most different
animations possible.
So this is what this will give me.
So basically, I'm requesting all the distance with my indices and asking to find me the
the worst one, and that becomes my new animations
I would start to train, and I get back the animations I want.
So I run this, it gives me a new feature vectors,
and I can see what it has done.
You see that it started already
to predict a bunch of stuff,
and it probably gets quite wrong on a lot of stuff, right?
quite wrong on a lot of stuff right it did it could detect that sometimes there
was contact but then so it detect that left leg fairly good but then still is
still in contact so pretty bad and when you only train a retail system so
basically what we have to do now is manually correct this clip and then
when this one will be corrected we could again concatenate with what we already
trained and then we can retrain a new classifier and we keep iterating this
way. To avoid doing that with you what I've done is that I've already went
through that process several times and I can just reload this data so basically
what I've done is that I've trained 10 different clips so out of my 22,000
frames have trained 2,000 frames.
And I can actually train my classifier with these values.
And if I tried to see what was the worst possible animations
it could find, this is the first thing.
So this is the one that we say is the worst animations
predictions possible.
And we could see that it's not too bad at what it predicted.
So the idea of this paper is just to stop as soon as when
it tells you that the worst frame is this one
and it's actually not wrong.
You could assume that you've finished training, basically,
with all the animation of data you have.
So this is how this paper works.
It's fairly efficient, I would say.
It's the first step into that machine learning concept,
because basically it's a classifier,
it's a model that you train, you fit data and you predict.
It's the basics of all machine learning systems.
So it was an interesting introduction
on all of the systems.
I haven't talked about key libraries and how they work and all that kind of stuff.
You could find a lot of videos about the system themselves and those libraries themselves
if you want to.
I hope you liked it and see you next time.